Okay.
So, first of all, welcome to Lamrim.
And Lamrim means steps up the path.
And
this is to me, you know, I was having
lunch.
I don't have anybody Okay, I was having
lunch with my with my wife's mother.
And
who passed away since then, but we were
and she had a boyfriend that she kicked
out later.
Which is what you should do with
boyfriends. Uh
And uh
we had lunch and we said, "What's the
greatest book in the world?
What's the greatest book in the whole
world?" And I love books.
And so it was difficult for me to
choose.
But I think this book we are studying
today is the greatest book in this
planet. It's the greatest book in this
world. I think so.
And my teacher taught it to me three
times.
It took 30 years.
And he went Every time he finished it,
he started again.
And he taught it in two different
places.
See, he had one group in Washington,
D.C.
And he had another group in near New
York. So
but I was his driver.
So I get to go to both of them. So I
heard him teach it for
30 years.
And it
Oh man, it's it's wonderful to learn it.
And it's a wonderful friend for your
whole life, okay? So keep this book
close to you.
And I know there's a great I think
there's a good Chinese translation and
you know, there's a good English
translation. I helped to do the English
translation.
So keep it close to you, use it, okay?
And I started teaching it 14 years ago.
And I promise I will finish it.
And if I survive few more days, Dodo
I will finish it. I'll keep my promise,
you know. So we will finish
this book this week
after 14 years of hard work.
So I'd like to give us a hand. Yay.
Yeah.
The tradition of this lineage is if you
sit in the audience, you have to teach
it next.
Okay, seriously. I'm not kidding, okay?
And I know
probably you didn't come to every single
class in 14 years.
I don't know if anybody did except me.
But uh
if you You want to just throw it?
In case I start to cry.
Uh
So
I ask you, you know, we are going to
finish this week.
And please, please, please teach it to
to other people, okay? So my
Wait.
My job is finished
this week, okay? For this book.
Then it's your responsibility,
okay? And you should teach it.
And even you weren't here the whole
time, it's okay.
You can
listen to the
audio or the video or
or you can read it. It's It's not that
difficult. It's better if you come to
the class, but if you didn't
I still expect you to teach the whole
thing, okay?
And just do your best. All the teachers
of the Lamrim
we just do our best, you know. We No
Nobody's perfect. Nobody's Buddha,
maybe.
And we just have to try, okay? So please
try.
And please teach it to your students and
your friends. I taught it to my
wife's mother.
If the son-in-law can teach to the
mother-in-law, then anyone can teach to
anybody.
Yeah. So
you know.
Okay?
We will finish this this week if if
Inshallah.
If all goes well. And uh
We were at the whole book is about 400
folios, which is 800 pages, which is
about 6,000 English pages.
Okay? The whole book is about 6,000
English pages.
And we are very, very close to
finishing. When I started teaching it
14 years ago
the last, last part of the book is about
meditation, how to do meditation.
And I thought it would be a good
strategy
to teach the end of the book first
14 years ago about shamatha and
vipashyana, about meditation, deep
meditation.
So I taught it first because you're
supposed to meditate
on each step of the path.
The book is called step up the path.
And each time you teach or teach teaches
you one step.
Then you're supposed to meditate on that
step. So seems to me logically
you should teach the meditation to your
students first.
Which is at the end of the book.
And then go through the book with them
and they can meditate on each section.
So it's a tradition to to do this, okay?
So we we got very, very far. We went
through three
great
sections.
Khibu chung, Khibu dung, Khibu chambo.
These are
different motivations
of people why they study this book. Some
people just want to stay out of the They
don't What do you call it? They don't
want to be a dog next time.
They want to stay out of the lower
place. By the way, minimum motivation
to be in this room
is to
I don't want to go down after I die,
okay? So
it's very unusual in this world
that
to get into the course
you have to be thinking about after your
death, okay? To get into to start the
course
you have to think about dying.
Okay? And that's very unusual in this
world. I went to Princeton University.
They don't have any course in how to
die.
But everybody have to die and it's the
most important thing you have to do.
It's very strange. There should be a PhD
in dying, right? So anyway
this book begins
on the day that you die, okay? And and
then it goes deeper and deeper, okay? So
minimum
motivation after I die
I don't want to go down, you know. I I
just
like to stay as a at least stay as a
human, you know. I would like to do
that. Everybody thinks they're going to
be a human in the next life.
First of all, in in my part of the
world, in the western part of the world
we don't believe that you live after you
die. We don't believe it.
We don't even believe this much, you
know. Those people who believe it
they say, "I hope
my I have as much hair as Stanley when I
come back.
And not as much hair as Geshe la
or John Brady.
So
you know, all the people thinking like
that, but to come back as a human
is
very, very rare, one out of a billion.
You know, if eight people in this world
come back as human, it's a pretty good.
You see, it's very
rare. So the purpose of this book
first of all, come back as a human, you
know. Then at least you can
keep coming to Tim's programs.
Okay?
Maybe you can find your old kimono.
You know.
That's minimum motivation, okay? And
then
second level motivation,
I don't want to
come back to a place where I have to
die.
I don't want to come back to a place
where I have to lose my family again.
And lose my mother again, you know. I
don't want to come back to a place like
that. I want to go to a place where
we don't have these problems, okay?
That's second motivation.
Then third motivation is I would like to
become Buddha.
Because a Buddha can really help
countless people at the same time. No
limit, no number.
Okay? And it's fun.
You know,
I I don't feel like it's a very serious
thing to become a Buddha.
I think it's a very fun thing
to become a Buddha. I enjoy to help
people, you know. I don't know. Today
I went to a coffee shop, you know. I I
clean up the coffee cups for the staff.
Right?
And I enjoy it, you know. But think if
you can help billions and billions of
people at the same time.
If you can babysit
for a whole planet.
That's my dream, you know. I I imagine
I'm sitting with my wife
somewhere just past the sky.
And we babysit my grandmother sometimes.
She's 2 years old. She's coming here uh
I hope in Sakura.
If the Sakura doesn't open, I'm going to
stay until it it opens.
Okay, Sophie Chao. If it
This time I'm on strike.
Uh
and then, you know, it's hard to babysit
one 2-year-old. She's
She's so cute. She We bought her
school bus this big.
And in America, all the school buses for
children is a yellow color, bright
yellow color.
And uh we bought her a school bus.
It It doesn't You can take off the top
of the roof of the bus.
And then there's many little kids and
and you
the 2-year-old puts the kids in the bus,
you know.
And she Maybe the one kid is driving or
like this and she put all the kids in.
And then she tried to get in the bus.
It's so cute, you know. She's like
Her name is Cece. Cece, passenger. Cece,
passenger, you know. And she's trying to
get into the bus with all the other
kids.
Yeah, it means she thinks she's this
big, right?
And
she couldn't get Her foot couldn't get
in the bus.
And she kept trying to push her foot in
the bus, you know. So, I mean, even to
take care of
one two-year-old
is it's a hard job for grandpa.
You know, when all the ladies leave and
they say, "Grandpa, watch the child."
I'm like,
You know.
But imagine uh 8 billion people. Imagine
you are babysitter
for 8 billion people. I like it. I think
I'm up for it. I I'm looking forward to
it, you know.
I I worked really hard
to become babysitter for 8 billion
people. And
I Do you know, you go to the headquarter
Buddha headquarters.
And they they give you a planet, you
know. Okay, where's my planet?
This one. Okay, I'm all right. I'll take
care.
Then you you actually watch the whole
planet. You take care of everybody.
And I think it's cool. Okay, that's the
ultimate
Lamrim steps of the path motivation.
That's final motivation. I I want to
babysit
a planet.
I want to take care of all the planet
people. I want to make sure they don't
get old and die.
You know, if anybody dies on my planet,
I I'm not a very good Buddha, you know.
I would like to
So, Jasmine's like
Her group is almost the whole planet,
but now she's thinking, "Now I have to
go bigger."
You know, I have to take the whole
planet.
So,
So, we're on that part, you know. We're
at the end of the book.
Uh we're teaching how to do planet
babysitting.
And uh there's a six famous perfections.
Uh six famous activities
that a body Bodhicitta means you decided
I want to babysit the planet, okay?
So, you you made a decision.
You know,
you not just think about your family or
not just think about your country.
You want to babysit the whole world,
okay? And it's really
It sounds difficult, but it's not. I
think one 2-year-old is more difficult.
Whole planet is easier, okay? And
what I want to say is it's fun, okay?
Like it's
It's nice to help someone not to die.
Uh but it's also I personally enjoy
having fun every day.
And what I do, I like to have fun. And I
can tell you
to be a Bodhisattva is the most fun
thing, okay? Like it's not very serious.
You all too serious.
Oh, death.
Save a planet from death.
I don't know.
Chenrezig
He our son. Chenrezig son.
You know,
uh
wolf warrior number three.
It feels like some hero, you know. Don't
think like that. It's just fun, okay?
It's like a big party, okay? It's the
best party you ever went to
uh to take care of 8 billion people,
okay? And it You don't feel stressed
out.
You feel like, "Waha, give me another
planet. This is One planet not enough,
you know. Okay, all right." So, we're
learning how to do that.
Uh and we are
We started and and we're going to
continue through there. There are six
uh activities uh Bodhisattva has to
learn.
And we're going to go through the six.
Uh
We already went through giving.
First one is called giving. Uh say dana.
Paramita.
Yeah, so the perfection of giving. And
we finished that one. Now we're on the
second one. Shila. Say shila.
Paramita. Okay. Yeah, morality or
ethics, okay?
Okay.
Uh and here we go.
Yeah, okay.
I
And by the way, I'm very proud everyone
came back after yesterday.
I thought some people will go to Tokyo
or something.
Uh the yesterday was a very difficult
class.
And uh I'm very proud that you came back
and I'm happy that you came back, okay?
Actually, yesterday is the test.
Uh if the people quit yesterday,
they don't come to the Lamrim class, you
see. So, we make the first class very
difficult.
Then the
I don't know.
The people who not serious will quit.
And and then the second class, we do the
real class, okay?
So, that's what we're doing today. All
right. Uh I'm going to show the
I'm going to show the
Himalaya language on the on the screen,
okay?
And I'm just putting seeds in your mind,
okay? So,
don't learn it. Don't think about it.
Okay?
I'm planning for your next life.
Okay? Uh
and you you think uh
you won't learn it, but you will.
And I agree, maybe you don't learn it in
this life.
But I'm planning for next life, okay?
So, I'm putting seeds in your mind.
Okay, only dodo can learn in 1 week how
to read it, okay? Other normal people,
not possible, okay?
So, you don't don't worry too much.
Don't take it seriously.
It's a very unusual language. By the
way, as a linguist who study languages,
this language
the there's an old tradition
that this language dropped out of the
sky.
And I believe it, okay? Linguistically,
it's not connected to any language in
the world. It's a very strange language,
okay?
Very unusual language, so.
And it's very good for
Buddhism. It's very good for teaching
Buddhism, okay?
All right.
Uh
So, here we go. I'll pronounce it. You
don't have to worry.
Don't get all
upset. It's not like your school days
are coming back or something like that,
okay? It's just I'm planting seeds for
next time. It will be easier to babysit
you next time
if you
if I put some seeds this time, okay? But
don't take it Don't go serious, okay?
Don't take it very serious, okay?
Okay, nipa tsultrim gyalpo chig nyam len
ni, okay? How do we practice the
perfection of
morality or ethical life, okay?
Perfection is a tricky word.
Uh the the
Sanskrit is paramita. Say paramita.
Yeah, and
Himalayan language is par ol tu chimba.
Par ol tu chimba. Say par ol tu chimba.
Yeah, good.
And um
it's a strange word because it it's
perfection.
Uh but it's not, okay? Perfection means
in this case, your morality is perfect.
You never got angry at anybody.
You never stole $5 from your mother. I
did.
Only once, okay?
Uh but something when you're a kid,
right? So, this kind of idea
uh you are perfect. It doesn't mean
that.
It means if you try,
it will take you to Buddhahood, okay? It
You This is a perfection
perfectionizer.
This is a make you perfect. It's not
perfection, okay? Nobody here, I don't
know,
is perfect about their morality, okay?
But we we want to be.
So, if you want to be, we can say
perfection. Par ol paramita.
Paramita is perfection, okay?
Uh and paramita means bottom.
In Sanskrit, bottom means
uh far side of the ocean. If you
are surfing like Rob
in Los Angeles and the you there's a big
storm and you
float out into the ocean
and your surfboard reaches Japan.
That's called bottom. Okay, that's
called bottom. You reach the other side
of the ocean. It means gone. You you
reached it.
There's a word in English exit.
It means to the place where you go out.
X means out. It means gone.
So the English comes from the Sanskrit.
Bottom eater. Bottom eater means to go
to the other side. Exit means to go out.
Okay.
All right. So then so that's the second
perfection.
When I teach
Lamrim steps of the path
I like to use pictures. Okay.
And I call them idea images
and the short name is item.
And I like to show a picture
then I like to teach you what the
meaning of the picture.
And then later when you are teaching
your own students is starting next week.
The picture help you remember. Okay. We
call mnemonic. It helps you remember.
Okay. Pictures are very helpful. One
picture is worth a
thousand words in English we say.
Okay. So here's a picture.
Uh
I got to hear you.
I call it the decision to throw out the
garbage. Okay. To to practice
ethical life.
You have to decide to throw out the
garbage. Let's see what that means.
Okay.
Then he quotes
Segius
book which is called
Bodhisattvacaryavatara
which means how to live like a
Bodhisattva. How to become a planet
babysitter.
Okay. How to become a the instruction
book.
How to become a babysitter of a whole
planet. Okay. That's called
Bodhisattvacaryavatara.
Segius translating it nowadays. Okay. It
was written
years ago.
Okay.
And I'll read it to you.
Boy 72 ballet children part of chinba
shin.
Uh
So this very important word called
Boy 72 say Boy
Boy 72
72 means mind.
Okay. 72 mind.
And then Boy means decision to give up
something. Boy means decision to give up
something. For example
You can Boy
meat eating meat. Okay. You can make a
decision.
I don't want to be involved
with the murder of of little in animals.
You know, I don't I I don't want to
participate. I don't want to be one of
those people. It's not who I want to be.
So you can Boy
eating meat. Okay. You can give up
eating meat.
My teacher
He's Tibetan. They eat meat a lot.
They they say we we cannot grow
vegetables. We are too high. The
mountains are too high. We cannot grow
vegetables. Therefore we eat meat. You
know, so
So
anyway
when I was living in the monastery I
gave up eating meat. At that time all
the other people eat meat.
And it was a little bit difficult.
And
when my teacher introduced me to other
teacher
he said this is Mike.
He give up meat but he didn't give up
his negative thoughts.
He make fun of me every time.
You know, I'm all right.
Uh
Then I'll tell you something
interesting.
So he ate meat his whole life.
And then when he was older maybe when he
was 75 something. Actually it's not old.
Um
He
uh
He had a
What do you call? He had to have an
operation.
And uh
Then he came home from the hospital and
he said
I'm going to give up meat. I was his
cook.
So I I I have to cook meat every day. I
don't eat it. I cook for him.
Then he said don't cook me meat. I said
why? You don't feel good? He said no.
I had the surgery and now I know what it
feels like.
He said and he never ate meat again.
You know, so he made fun of me for 30
years.
Then then at the end he said you know
what? I think I'll give up meat. I'm
like what?
You know, and that's called Boy. Okay.
Say Boy.
Boy means you decide to give up
hurting other people. Okay. You decide
to give it up. Boy means I made a
decision. What?
I I just don't want to hurt people. You
know, I'm not going to hurt people
anymore. I'm going to do my best
that I don't hurt people anymore. Okay.
And sometimes if you have some terrible
pain yourself like if you go to a
hospital and the doctor
rearrange this your stomach.
If they cut you, you know, then you get
more compassion for
animals and and things like that. You
see?
So often times
Boy comes from
you feel sad. You know, you feel
suffering. When you have bad suffering
then finally you you wake up. You know,
I I don't want to cause suffering to
other
beings. You know, I I I want to try to
help them. I don't want to kill them or
cut them
like that. Okay. That's called Boy. Give
up
the decision
to give up hurting other people is the
second perfection.
It is the second perfection. Sheila.
Morality.
Ethics. Okay. I'm I'm tired.
Uh
There's a beautiful beautiful I'll get
there.
Um
Sheila Nupa Shida Chepa say Sheila.
Nupa
Shida
Chepa
That's
able to read by a real roach.
Okay, good.
All right. They gave me a screen but
it's like this big.
Okay. Okay. Sheila Nupa Shida Chepa very
say Sheila.
Nupa Shida
Chepa
Very very very very famous. Okay.
Jetsun Kapa
600 years ago wrote
the most famous summary of morality.
Okay. Very very very famous. And in fact
one of our translators translated it for
5 years.
Shopping?
Yeah, she finished it. And it took the
commentary very Yeah.
Very difficult commentary.
She finished very difficult and she
finished it.
So anyway in his famous poem
Tsongkhapa says
the definition of ethics the definition
of morality
the definition of the second perfection
is here. Sheila Nupa Shida Che
Sheila Shida Che Dopa Nupa Shida Che
Sugye Tupa Supa Boy 72
means uh
when you decide to give up hurting
other beings.
That's morality. That's ethics. Then
Tsongkhapa said something very
interesting.
Shida Chepa say Shida Chepa.
So
traditionally
in the
ancient ancient schools of Buddhism
Abhidharma
morality is
physical and verbal.
Morality is physical and verbal. I will
not kill.
I will not steal.
I will not have sex with another
person's partner.
Those
are physical. Then verbal. You know, I
will not lie. I will not slander. I will
not use harsh words. I will not gossip.
Those those seven
three three with your body and four with
your mouth. By the way, which is more
difficult to control?
I think mouth much more difficult to
control. Okay. So giving up these seven
is the ancient ancient form of morality.
Okay. But there's missing something.
What's that?
Yeah, what are you doing in your mind?
In the ancient forms of Buddhist
morality
they focus on what you do and what you
say.
And then when Tsongkhapa taught it
he said Shida Che. Say Shida Che.
Along with the foundation
along with the mother cause of talking
and doing things. What's the mother
cause of talking and doing things?
It's you're thinking.
And and some commas like you cannot
leave that out of the perfection of
morality.
Okay, you can say morality is what you
do
and morality is what you say.
But in Buddhism
the most important part of morality is
what you think.
Okay? And you can break your morality
and nobody around you knows you are
doing it, right? Inside your own mind
you can think terrible things.
Sometimes we surprised, you know? Wow.
I didn't know I could think such
terrible thing.
You know, sometimes thought come in your
in your mind, you know, I would like to
run this person over with a big car.
You know, and then you're like, oh yeah.
You know? So, sometimes your mind makes
terrible things. Your mind decide to do
that. You never do it. You never say it,
but your mind thinks it, right? It's
secret. Nobody else knows, right?
That's also morality in Buddhism, okay?
So, you know
Shila chepa is a very famous
very very famous addition
uh by Tsongkhapa.
Hurting people with your body
hurting people with your words
and the thinking behind those two. He
he's very clear.
To decide to give up those things is
morality.
Komba say komba.
Uh g o m s, okay? Say komba.
Now, if there's a g or a b on that word,
it means meditate, okay? Gom. Gom ba
means meditate. If you take off the b
and you take off the s
it means get used to something. To get
used to something. The uh Tibetan word
for meditation
is from the ancient word to get used to
something. To get used to doing
something, okay? So, we can say that
meditation the deeper meaning
of meditation is to get used to doing
something a certain way, okay? That's
called meditation in the ancient. And
it's also in the Sanskrit. Say bhavana.
Like but you are totally bhavana.
Bhavana.
Okay, bhavana means uh bhava means to
be.
Ana means to do.
Bhavana means it makes you into
something new.
And that's the word for meditation in
Sanskrit, okay? Bhavana
the word for meditation in Sanskrit
means to make you into somebody new.
It's a very beautiful word, okay? And
the Tibetan is similar, komba.
Okay? So, here he says
uh
the perfection of wisdom perfection of
morality
is when you get really good at it, okay?
You get really good
at being careful
not to hurt other people, okay? Super
careful not to hurt other people. That's
morality. That's ethics, okay?
All right. Mm, he gave you a definition.
All right. Now, he's going to give uh
this After you give a definition,
normally you give the different kinds.
What's the different kinds of ethics? In
Buddhism
there's three different kinds of ethics,
okay? In Buddhism in general
okay?
By the way, I have a lot of old DCI
friends here.
You know
different
projects we have.
It's so fun
to be able to talk about Buddhism.
I feel so really good.
Just in this room, okay? Yeah, okay.
It's like getting out of prison or
something, okay?
Uh so, there are three kinds of sutra,
okay? There are three kinds of shila
uh morality, okay? By the way, the
Sanskrit word for morality, shila
comes from an ancient root shil, which
means
to feel
refreshingly cool. Today when I was
walking
in the city
it's a shila day.
It's not too hot. It's not too cold.
It's just kind of
pleasant We call crisp in English.
Like crisp vegetable. It feel like a
crisp apple.
It's it's that kind of nice feeling.
Shila means that. The real meaning means
shila to to calm down your mind
to put your bad thoughts in the
refrigerator.
It's called shila, morality, okay?
All right.
So, here he says shila has three kinds.
Nature don't be too to me. The first
kind
the most basic kind
of Buddhist morality is don't hurt other
people, okay? The There's three levels
of Buddhist morality. Nature means bad
behavior.
And the first level of Buddhist morality
is look
even you can't be a bodhisattva
you know, even you cannot give someone
your arm
at least don't hurt people, okay? At
least don't hurt people. That's called
nature don't be too to me. First kind of
morality, don't hurt other people, okay?
Uh don't be too to me double day.
And then he's going to give
uh
He says
Now, I have a financial problem. I gave
away all my money yesterday, right?
You got anything else in there?
Just
He's like a magician.
Never mind.
You got?
And let's find some money, okay? We have
a hundred?
Let's do a hundred, okay?
I'll have to get more investors, okay?
Uh
lam den nay
No, no, I'm not asking for money.
I'm really not asking for money.
I just need to go to the bank.
Okay,
uh lam den nay don't be too to me double
day. Yeah.
He says
uh
the morality of not hurting other people
comes in three different flavors, like
chocolate, vanilla, and strawberry.
Okay? The morality of not hurting other
people comes in three different flavors.
All three
classical
types of vows
reflect the morality of not hurting
other people, basically, okay?
Basically. Now for a hundred dollars
and don't yell out the answer. I don't
pay for yelling. I pay for hands.
Okay? Uh what are the three traditional
types of vows?
Okay?
I don't I I am not choosing. Whoever
the microphone guy chooses.
Then you have to give him half the
money.
No, I'm kidding.
Wait.
You
Wait, wait, wait, wait. Where's the s
tech guys?
Can you turn on this microphone? Uh
There we go. Okay. Talk loud.
Kiss the microphone.
I believe it's the pratimoksha vow.
Good. The bodhisattva vow. 66. And that
the diamond way vow. Good. Hundred
dollars.
Uh Buddhist vows
uh come in three flavors, like
chocolate, vanilla ice cream.
Uh strawberry. Uh
so, first one is called pratimoksha
vows. Basically, don't hurt other
people, okay? Second level of vows
is bodhisattva vows, okay? These are
interesting vows. The bodhisattva vows
they are
uh promises 64 promises you make
for the rest of your life to help other
people. To be nice to other people. The
The first level of vows are just don't
hurt other people.
Okay? Like control yourself.
And then the second level of vows
is plant the seeds in your own mind to
become a planet babysitter.
Bodhisattva vows, okay?
Bodhisattva vows.
And I mentioned it yesterday, I guess.
We're going to do a bodhisattva vows
ceremony here. Some of my friends
uh asked me to give them bodhisattva
vows. I don't usually do it. I usually
subcontract
uh this kind of work. But
uh
there's a place an hour from here called
Nana, isn't it?
And this is where
uh the great
first one of the first Chinese masters
who came to Japan, whose name is
Say again.
That guy.
Uh
He six times he tried to get to Japan.
Six times his boat five times his boat
broke.
Very beautiful story. Then when he got
here
the first thing one of the first things
he did, he went to the emperor
and his friends and he gave them
bodhisattva vows. That temple is still
here in Kyoto.
I went there. It's very beautiful with
my friends and uh
so, I thought
me and Stanley also we thought it would
be fun to give Bodhisattva vows
at that exact place where where he was
standing.
So, it's in March.
Yeah. When the Sakura
flowers open, the Bodhisattva vows will
open. What?
We're still working on the date and we
need special permission from the
government
to have a ceremony there and if they
don't give permission, we'll just rent a
hotel next door, okay?
Don't worry about it.
Or we'll go on a on the beach.
Okay.
All right.
Anyway, that's the second kind of vow.
Third vow is secret vows, okay? Secret
vows. Secret vows are Bodhisattva vows.
What do you call it?
Supercharged Bodhisattva vows.
Super Bodhisattva vows, okay? And
my You want to know how my teacher
introduced those vows?
He said, "The third kind of vow is a
secret vows and that's secret."
But
I will be teaching them next year.
Okay, somehow. All right. Now here he
says, "I will give you a quotation from
uh
Atisha, okay?
Uh
and this is a famous book
uh that was written one exactly 1,000
years ago.
Okay. And Lam Kye Don Ma
Bodhi Patha Pradipika.
Uh Bodhi Patha Pradipa, which means the
light on the path of the to Buddhahood,
okay? Bodhi Patha Pradipa.
And he says, "So So Ter Ma Ri Dün Kyi Ta
Tu Dön Chen Dem Ba La Chan Ju Sem Pa Dön
Ba Yi Kya Wa Yö Kyi Shen Dön Min." Okay,
very famous uh
definition
of different kinds of
first level morality, different kinds of
vows, okay?
So So Ter Ma Ri Dün Kyi
So, there's
the first
set of vows you take is called So So Ter
Ma. In Sanskrit, it's
Prati Pratimoksha, okay? Pratimoksha and
it means
individual
freedom. Prati means one by one.
Moksha means freedom.
Okay?
And $100. Why is it called one by one
freedom?
We got this much money, honey?
Oh, okay.
So, it is the path
Wait. Start over again.
Um it's can remove your mental
afflictions and it's the path to
Nirvana.
What does one by one?
Prati Pratimoksha. You gave me the
moksha part. I need the prati part.
That's $50.
What's prati Why one by one?
Wait, Shamar.
Gibson?
Those individually who keep these vow
will get freedom.
And?
You gave me $25 answer. She gave me 50.
Oh, and those who do not keep the vow
Good. Yeah, now we're up to 100.
But I'm not giving it to anybody.
I'm not like wildly generous. I'm I'm
making a deal.
Yeah, Pratimoksha means
if you
protect the vows
if you keep those vows
you will reach Nirvana. And if you do
not keep the vows, you will not reach
Nirvana. Therefore, they are called
individual freedom vows. Individual
means those individuals who keep them
get freedom. Those individuals who don't
keep them
they don't get freedom, okay? Cool.
Uh now
Atisha said
there's a seven types of Pratimoksha
vows, okay?
And that's a little bit controversial,
okay? It's not seven.
Okay?
Uh
And we have to explain it. We have to
talk about it, okay? And so I made some
notes for you, okay?
Here's the seven that Atisha's talking
about. Atisha did not include
the one-day vow.
He said, "Look, one-day vow
come on, it's one day.
Why should we count that?"
So, normally we say there's eight kinds
of Pratimoksha vows.
Normally we say one-day vow is the first
one.
But Atisha said, "Yeah, one day, who
cares?"
All right. So, he doesn't include it in
his poetry here, okay? He says seven
types, okay?
Here's the seven. Number one.
Uh
The person who agree for their whole
life
to keep like 10 vows or eight vows,
okay? Then that's lifetime
male is number one, okay? In the modern
world, I think we should say
lifetime female vows number one.
Okay?
Uh these vow Those are so ancient vows
that come from the times in India when
the females did not have equal rights
and the men have more rights. So, I I
like to switch it.
Okay? And then secondly, uh the male
who keeps a lifetime vows, layman's
vows, okay? Those are the two first two
of the
seven, okay?
Uh third one is uh
Genyen
Ma
and that's like um
Oh, sorry. That's the second one. Getsul
Ma
which means novice
nun.
Getsul Ma and then a novice monk, okay?
They keep like I don't know
10, 15 vows, okay? Like that, okay?
And then uh
full
Uh I'm sorry. Then there's another
category number five, right?
That's called intermediate nun, okay?
So, for nuns
it was more difficult to become a full
nun. They had to show more serious and
keep their vows longer.
So, first they got basic vows, then they
got medium vows and then they got full
vows, okay?
And then six and seven is full monk and
full nun, okay? Full nun, all right.
Mi Gang Ngö Chö Tsasum Nam Bö Wa Che Pa
Gye Long Ngö
253 vows for full monk.
Sung Ga Dü Kyi Tsashin Nam
Bö Wa Che Pa Gye Long Ngö
for nuns. Why nuns have more? They are
more intelligent and they can keep track
of more vows.
There.
The nuns told me how to teach it that
way, okay?
All right. Okay, we had some
discussions.
Um
Okay.
Oh, let's do the rest of his verse. Let
me see here. As So Ter Ma Dön De
Dön De Dön Chen Dem Ba La Chan Ju Sem Pa
Dön Ba Yi Kya Wa Yö Kyi Shen Dön Min.
Now he says an interesting thing. As uh
Atisha
says uh
if you keep one of these seven sets of
vows, like if you promise to keep vows
for the rest of your life, like the 10
vows, even the 10 vows
he says, "That person
is
ready for Bodhisattva vows."
Okay?
Do Do you understand what just happened
in this room?
All of you who dreaming to take
Bodhisattva vows where the emperor took
them
from the great Chinese master
now you have to do some
I trick you to do the other vows also.
You understand? You cannot take
Bodhisattva vow
unless you agree to keep the basic
morality vows, okay? So, that's easy,
right?
Okay? Understand?
Yeah. I'm trying to read the contract to
you.
Okay? If you agree to take 64
Bodhisattva vows, which are fun. Dr.
Shin Ma Chin Ngö Mi Tri Shag Gön Min De
Chen Bö Wa Dön Gye Ngö Dön Chö Chö Ngö
Dön Min.
You know
they're fun vows, super fun vows.
But you still have to agree to the basic
10 vows, okay? Don't kill, don't steal.
Don't mess around with other people's
wife or husband, like that, okay? Easy.
Understand?
All right.
Okay, you don't get Bodhisattva vows
without basic morality vow.
All right.
Uh Chan Ju Sem Pa Dön Ba Yi Kya Wa Yö
Kyi Shen Dön Min. Kya Wa say Kya Wa.
Kya Wa means
uh
it's a difficult word and it means do
you have the karma to come back here in
Sakura and take your Bodhisattva vows?
Do you have enough good karma? Or will
the airplane be late?
Or you will your boss will tell you you
have a project
or you know, your bank account will go
like my bank account below zero.
You see what I mean? Like that. Kawa
means
good luck or something like that. Do you
have the good luck to come back here and
get those vows, okay? And and that's I
cannot say.
That's something inside your own mind.
Okay, what's the karma inside your mind?
You know, it's billions of years old. I
have no idea, you know. Will you die
before March? Will I die before We don't
know.
Okay, so kawa means do you have the
enough good karma to be here?
Uh do you have enough good karma to get
here?
And and it's we don't know, okay? We
hope so, right? I mean, if you make a
prayer
to be here, it it helps you to get the
karma. You see what I mean?
If you say, "Boy, I really like to do
that." That helps you get the karma to
come. You see what I mean? Okay?
Uh so, just to get here is just to get
here
Look, he crashes boat five times.
He's a great master, you know. It's what
Laozi
Dashi Laozi.
I'm not supposed to say.
What's that word? Da
Da wang.
Okay, anyway, you understand.
Uh if a great master crashes boat five
times to get here for the Bodhisattva
vows, maybe you have flight delay.
Okay, I say you should leave the day
before.
Okay, don't don't make a tight flight,
okay? Something will try to stop you.
And make plans. Make strange plans.
Like
come here 1 week before and
try to visit every French restaurant in
Kyoto.
That's my plan. Okay.
Uh
Shen pei shibing How are we doing on
time? Timothy, when do I have to stop?
Huh? 4:04 5?
5:00 p.m.?
Seriously?
Okay, good. Okay, just shut me up if I
If I don't shut myself up, you shut me
up. Okay, shibing was in my
Uh
chang chu dong la shang shang dong la me
de na su da ge su me ge be da wo su ba
ni
Uh
It's saying it seems to be It's saying
that in order to get Bodhisattva vows,
you should have
basic morality vows, okay? One of those
seven times. Okay? Usually in some
couple's form, it's eight times.
Why he includes one deva, okay?
Uh na ge ga na du ba du ba de na ge lon
cho to she ba shin. This is interesting.
Uh
when you practice the secret teachings,
which we will call Diamond Way teachings
Vajrayana, say Vajrayana.
Yeah, uh
when you
practice the secret teachings, they say
uh
if you are uh
ordained
if you're a monk or nun
uh you get a head start.
That's the You get like extra credit,
okay? It's easier.
It's It's It's not necessary
to be a monk or a nun to get the
to get the secret vows. It's not
necessary.
Anybody in this room can get them.
If you have Bodhisattva vows.
But if you get Bodhisattva vows, you got
to Yes.
Uh
anyone can take them, but uh the best
chance of success is if you're a monk or
nun, okay? Traditionally, they say that,
okay?
But everyone can take them. Why? Now,
you tell me why.
According to this theory
the whole theory we've been talking
about today
Yeah, the more morality you're trying to
keep
the better you will keep your secret
vows, okay? Like if you have 253 vows or
364 vows
Like I don't know.
We had trouble translating those
nuns' vows are complicated.
Don't tie up your spice bags with
threads.
It took us like a month to figure out
that one.
I'm not going to tell you. You have to
get the book.
Okay,
Anyway, a monk or a nun is supposed to
supposed to be they have so many vows,
they are more careful. They are used to
being careful about small things. In my
time, my spice bags with a thread
wrongly.
Okay, so supposedly they can
succeed in the Diamond Way. But
everyone in this room can study Diamond
Way, can take Diamond Way vows, okay? By
the way, you cannot study Diamond Way
if you don't take the Diamond Way vows,
understand?
It's like a prerequisite.
Okay,
let me get lon cho to she ba shin chang
sem ge la ba
lo be de cho la gom ba le number tan je
le ni ma en de. But
uh
in general
there are people chang sem ge la ba lo
be de be ge be ta la lu yang nyon.
There are There have in history
there have been nagas
which are basically dragons, long.
Okay, but smart dragons, okay?
Uh and there are devas.
They are worldly gods who did take the
Bodhisattva vows, okay? They They were
They were able to practice the
Bodhisattva teachings, okay? So, it's
not necessary
you have to be a human
uh if if
to get those vows, okay?
All right, o na kang da she ge she na.
Well, what's best?
Uh so ta ge dong de chang sem ge la ba
lo ba she yi na so ta ge dong ba de na
tu mo en dong dong de ga be dong be tu
ten na me sem je.
Uh
generally
uh
any kind of morality which prepares you
for your Bodhisattva morality
is called is kind of special
pratimoksha, okay?
So, in general
you don't have to take Bodhisattva vows
to be a nun or a monk, for example. But
those monks and nuns who took the
Bodhisattva vows
their monks' vow and their nuns' vow is
even more powerful, okay? They got
upgraded to business class.
What's
first class?
Diamond Way, okay? Diamond Way. Okay,
good.
All right, so ta dong de mi na mi ge chi
pong ge pong dong la dong be tu ten su
jo.
Uh
Some people say, "Look, Geshe la
what's the lowest kind of pratimoksha
vow?"
What is the lowest kind of pratimoksha
vow?
Yeah, you could say uh
one one deva, okay?
Uh
or generally
it's like agreeing to
five lifetime layman's vows. Basically,
five promises. I will not kill a human
being.
Uh I will not steal anything valuable.
I will not specifically have sex with
another person's
husband or wife.
Uh I will not lie about seeing
emptiness.
Those are the four
basic basic ones, okay? And then number
five
Huh?
Yeah,
say it again.
I I agree not to use alcohol
or drugs, chemical drugs. And by the
way, the ancient Vinaya books says
alcohol or chemical drugs
or marijuana, etc., okay? I agree never
to use them in my whole life again,
okay?
And you know
I was not born a Buddhist. I I was born
a Christian and I was a happy Christian.
And
uh I had a good experience in the church
and um
but I
you know, many of my friends I I say
when when I got to study with my lama
for 30 years, you know,
uh
he said the first rule, you cannot
drink.
You know, you you cannot drink again in
your lifetime.
And I I almost bowed down to him at that
time.
I'm like 20 years old or something.
And I'm like, "God bless you." Oh, I
mean, Buddha bless you.
You know,
he's like, "Why?" And I say, "Alcohol
ruined my family."
You know, alcohol ruined my mother.
Alcohol ruined my father. I I spent 20
years
watching alcohol ruin my parents and
ruin the happiness of our family.
And God bless, this is I love Buddhism.
This is great.
You know,
I This is a good start. You know, if if
you guys say
the lowest morality
includes
never drinking any alcohol again. I'm
with you guys.
This is a good system.
Okay, cuz I saw as a child, I saw what
the alcohol did to two good people. They
were good people. They were nice people.
But alcohol make them worse and worse
and worse and then, you know, like that,
okay?
So,
don't come to Geshe La and say, "What
about if I want to have a glass of wine
with my grandmother?"
There's a trick.
You take the wine and you if you go to
your grandmother's house and she wants
to drink wine, you offer her wine, you
pour a wine for yourself, and then
accidentally you spill it, okay? I'm
teaching you how to do it.
I did it many times.
The floor is all purple.
Okay.
Uh Sutim done. Yeah.
Uh you can make it to Sutim to do. So,
therefore,
uh there's a famous uh exception in
Buddhism. If you don't feel like taking
a vow,
you don't have to.
Just agree to keep the 10
basic types of morality that all
Buddhists have to keep, okay? You don't
even have to take a vow.
Just in your mind say, "I will keep the
good deeds. I will try to do the 10 good
deeds."
Let's And by the way, I prefer to tell
I prefer to make that list positive
than to make that list negative. I don't
like to say no killing,
you know, no stealing. I like to say,
protect life.
Protect other people's things.
Respect other people's marriage, you
know, tell the truth.
Uh
always encourage people.
Always say sweet things to people. Don't
waste your talk with a blah blah, you
know, keep your mouth shut. Uh
then don't be happy when other people do
get stuff Don't be unhappy when other
people get stuff. Don't be happy when
other people lose stuff.
And finally,
you know,
basically understand karma, okay? Follow
karma.
Those are the positive 10.
You don't have to take a vow. Okay? If
you keep those 10,
uh you can still be a bodhisattva, okay?
It's like the cheap way
to be a bodhisattva. Okay? You don't
have to take vows, okay? Got it?
As a basis. All right. Mm,
that's uh
Nets don't worry Sutra. Nets don't worry
Sutra means I agree not to hurt people.
Okay? Now, what do you think is the
second level of morality? The The first
level is please, at least don't hurt
other people. What's the second level?
Easy.
Help people. Yeah, just help people. We
went to give a talk at ESAN, which is
the main business university in Peru.
The national business university. We
gave a talk there. We had breakfast with
the president of the university.
You were there.
And uh
he said, "Can I ask you a question?" You
know, and I said, "What?" He said,
"What's the different kinds of ethics in
Buddhism?"
And I'm like,
"Glad you asked."
Nets don't worry Sutra, okay? At least
don't hurt other people.
Then Gewa Choduk Sutra,
help other people. And then what?
We'll get there.
Okay, Gewa Choduk Sutra means all the
different kinds of morality to help
other people, okay?
And here's a list, okay? I still got 10
minutes, right, Kim?
Uh
It can include
a person who took their bodhisattva vows
and just goes into a temple. We call
Chinjay meet the Dharma.
You know, I When I first walked into my
teacher's temple,
I'm like, "Wow, that's nice.
I like that painting." He's like,
"You don't know how to meet the a
temple?" I was I'm like, "What?"
He says, "You don't know how to meet a
temple?" I said,
"How do you meet a temple?" He says,
"First of all, you got to go like this,
you know?" He like hit me. That was the
first day.
I I don't know if his hand wore out or
my head wore out.
But he's like, "You don't even know how
to walk into a temple. You're so stupid,
you know? You You go like this, okay?
It's called meeting the Dharma.
We don't say visit a temple.
We say meet the Dharma, okay? And And
you got to have your finger your thumbs
inside. You get in trouble this This
you're born as an animal with paws.
Okay.
And And you walk around the temple. And
nice to meet you, Tara. Nice to meet
you, Manjushri.
You look cool, Avalokiteshvara.
Okay. All right.
All right. All right.
Just doing that is the second kind of
morality.
Okay? Just holding your hands properly
in a temple is the second kind of
morality.
Uh Koti Rimdo, show respect for your
teacher and
show respect to the other students in
the class, okay? That's That's
basic morality.
Uh second level morality. Koti Rimdo,
Tsa Sum Gom Drup, sitting in the class
is the second kind of morality.
Okay? Cuz you are making good karma.
Just sitting here, you are making good
karma. Even if you fall asleep in the
class, you're making good karma.
Okay? Jet lag good karma.
Okay. Yay.
Class is over. Oh, yeah.
Okay.
Tsa Sum Gom Sum. Okay? Then just
studying, just doing your meditation,
and thinking thinking also I say
thinking on the plane, you know, on the
way home.
Think about what you heard, you know?
And that's a That's a kind of morality,
you see? That's a kind of Buddhist
morality.
Tsa Sum Gom Drup, Chay Chay Nying Chepa.
And then later, Chay Chay. Say Chay
Chay.
You have to teach. You have to teach,
okay? There's a
There's a
agreement
in a Buddhist teaching. There's a basic
contract between the teacher and the
student since 2 and 1/2 thousand years
ago.
Okay? If you sit in the class,
by sitting in the class,
you agree to teach later.
Okay? You're not allowed to sit in the
class
if you don't agree to teach later. You
don't Listen.
$100. Where did Geshe La give his first
Buddhist teaching?
Both wrong. He sat in the back of the
car. He said Volkswagen.
Forget it. Cancel it. Cancel $100 bet.
It was a bug, bochito.
If you are Mexican, you know what I'm
talking about.
The little Volkswagen.
You say Volkswagen is is not make $100.
Yes, it was a Volkswagen.
There's many Volkswagen. There's big
Volkswagen.
I'm talking bochito.
Bochito is a beetle, yeah. It It fits
one person comfortably.
Yeah, my first class
was the postman.
The The mail deliver
bang on the door. He said, "Can I ask
you a question?" I said, "I gave you a
tip last month."
He's like, "I'm not asking for more
money."
By the way, in America, you're not
supposed to give
tip to the postman. But if you don't,
sometimes the mail gets lost. Do you
understand?
Okay.
I'm just telling you about Rimrock's
family.
Okay.
So, anyway, uh I'm like I I gave you a
tip last month. He said, "No, no.
What are you guys doing here?" I said,
"This is a Buddhist temple. We study
Buddhism." He says, "Can I study
Buddhism?"
Then I said, "Are you serious?" He said,
"Yeah, I really want to learn, you
know?"
And he was my first student.
And I asked my teacher, uh "Can I teach
him in the kitchen?"
And my teacher said, "No.
I don't want the postman in here."
Then I "You go out in the bochito.
He sit in the back, you sit in the
front, you teach him."
Then it's very hard on the neck.
Okay. So, when I say you have to teach
Buddhism, because you learn You have to
teach Lamrim
because you learn Lamrim.
I mean,
also in the coffee shop and also at your
family's dinner table on New Year's or
something, okay? Like that.
And you don't have to say, "Do you know
there's three kinds of morality? There's
484 vows and there's 225." But But
there's a difference, you see? You know,
not like that. Just encourage other
people to be nice people,
then you're teaching Buddhism. Okay?
That's how you start.
You know, you just have dinner, make a
hot pot for your family.
If you're in America, make Thanksgiving
dinner.
Give fill them up with good food.
Then say, "By the way, do you think it's
okay to kill things or not?" You know,
like just
gently teach something.
Then then you you made the That's here,
okay? Chö chos nyen means teach
Buddhism.
Even as a friend in a car.
It It doesn't mean you have to get up in
front of It It took me 50 years to find
you guys.
Okay? You're not going to find 200 300
people
in in 2 weeks.
Okay? Don't think like that. Okay? Teach
one person
on the airplane. They can't get away.
You know, do you have your seat belt on?
Yeah. Let me tell you about morality.
Okay. Go sing gay way chawa na sam ta ta
che. Yeah, all those are called
second level ethics, okay?
Do na rang shing ge gyu mem che pa
chindu ge che pa kun de yin.
All attempts to practice the six
perfections, whether you are trying to
help yourself or help other people,
are morality.
All attempts to practice the six
bodhisattva activities is morality.
Okay? Normally in English, morality
means don't kill people.
Don't drive your new Tesla 100 miles an
hour and down the road.
I have a Chinese friend who did that.
He bought new car.
He didn't know how fast it can go.
Never mind, I won't embarrass him.
Uh
maybe I already did.
Okay, we got one more sentence. Uh
Gyal sing ge chö pa tam che su ten na ma
sum ge du shing.
Uh all the activities of a bodhisattva
are one of the three kinds of morality.
Shing na lam gyi rim pa tam che su ten
na ma sum nyi je pel gyur tong yin.
Just coming to Lamrim class, steps of
the path class, just learning about the
steps of the
path
is morality itself.
Okay? Learning the steps of the path
in this
class for 14 years,
every day that you sat there,
you were practicing morality. It's
morality to try to be a good person.
That's morality, okay? Cool.
Uh let's see. I still got 2 minutes,
Tim.
Sem gyi ge don che pa su ten na du shing
chö pa la so pa de.
Uh the third level of morality. So, the
first one is just avoid hurting other
people.
The second one is try to help other
And the third one is try to help
everybody in the world, okay? Try to
help everybody, okay? And there's a
special
practice for that.
Uh it's called doing öpa she. Say du we
öpa
she.
Okay? And these are the four ways
to treat your students.
Okay? These are the
famous four ways to treat your students,
okay?
And they're very beautiful.
And if you're
if you sit in this class,
and if you learn the steps of the path,
you have a moral responsibility to share
it with other people.
And in Buddhism, we say, "If they want
it."
Okay? If they want it. We're not allowed
to bother other people with our
religion.
Oh,
"Are you Jewish? You want to know about
Buddhism?
I'm the one to tell you." And they're
like, "Actually, no, I don't want to
know."
Then as a Buddhist, we're not supposed
to bother We're not allowed to bother
people who don't want to hear about it,
okay?
You You have to ask sweetly.
Do You're on the plane, right? Do you
want to hear what I just heard in Kyoto?
And the person say, "No, I'm texting my
mother." Okay.
You know, but if they say, "I want to
learn,"
then then we have a responsibility to
share, okay? So, that's
that's a big difference, I think.
In In where I live,
we have different religion people come
to my door.
And they they, you know, my wife can't
say no. I can say no very easy.
Uh
And she she learned She had some good
friends now that she made this way.
You know, she said, "Come in. Come in."
She gives them cake. She gives them
coffee. She talks about religion with
them. And And they enjoy.
But we're not allowed to do that. That's
why traditionally we offer mandala
before the class. If the student offer
the mandala,
it means I want to learn,
okay? Please teach me.
And if they if they don't offer the
mandala, we're actually not supposed to
teach, okay? It means nobody asked me to
teach.
Now,
if you fly to Kyoto and you come and sit
here for 1 hour,
I'm guessing you want to learn.
So, I'm I feel comfortable to teach you,
okay? Even without mandala. But
traditionally, we should do a mandala,
okay? All right. So, we're going to take
a break. When we come back, we have to
talk about the four ways
of sharing Dharma with other people,
okay?
And how long's the break, Tim?
30-minute break because there'll be a
traffic jam at the bathroom.
Okay, have a nice break.
Okay.